soft engineering radio episode 118 Wilco
visual on parsers
[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
support
[Music]
welcome wherever you are my name is
Lawrence strata today we're at the
cogeneration conference in Cambridge and
my guest is eel Cove issue we're going
to be talking today about passing and so
it's gonna that ilk I do a quick little
introduction tell you where he's from
hi Laurey yeah so my name is illigal
viscera I'm a work at Delft University
of Technology which in the Netherlands
and I'm associate professor there and I
had a group of digi students and
postdocs doing research into language
engineering software corporation
management and stuff like that ok so a
lot of our listeners will have heard
about passing they'll know that that
passing goes on somewhere it's this
magical term so could you give us an
introduction to passing you know why we
want to do it a what roughly it does and
we'll go into more detail as we go along
all right so so the general idea of
parsing is that you have a are typically
a textual representation you have a text
in some language and you want to do some
processing on that so you want to get at
the structure of the text and this is
the structure underlying the text
so typically you write a program that's
reached the carriers with the text and
make sense of its makes a structured
representation of that is this a little
bit with natural language we're
implicitly well you know when we talk we
sort of unbreak apart a sentence this is
the verb the noun and that sort of thing
the subject exactly said it's there's
actually called barging in natural
language linguistic theory what parsing
is from from dividing sentences up into
parts and they're making little tree
structures that
so that's exactly of parsing is about
and butter also all kinds of places in
in computing where you do it to think of
a text file with lines and then where
you have kind of columns separated by
tabs or colons or something like that
then you want to get the elements from
the from the columns and you write a
little program that gets the elements
from the for the columns my reading the
characters and you can be seeing where
the divisions are and and and translated
into some kind of tabular form so even
you know breaking up a CSV file is a
passing of us exactly exactly
okay so we're the sort of places that I
mean that's obviously giving us quite a
wide range what what are the sort of
places where typical user is going to be
using passing maybe even if they don't
know about it well exactly all those
places were never even so even I mean
reading in a string from a Proform in a
way in a web application but when you
and blue see where it is actually a
correct sentence according to whatever
you want in that place uniform yet
that's recognition right so you want to
say well this should this string shoots
[Music]
comply with this particular language you
should look like this it should be an
email address I should have a bunch of
letters and an @ symbol and then a bunch
of other letters and a adult and some
more and stuff enough and so that's
that's already a place where you might
come across parsing problem
I can't obviously people probably often
thinking about it in terms of things
like compilers and and that sort of
thing as you saying it's just it's used
pretty much everywhere ever anyone is
dealing anything with text that goes
into a computer exactly okay so as I
said earlier a lot of our listeners and
a lot of people in general have that
will have the general feeling that
passing is a pretty hard topic it's one
of those things that people often run
away in fear so why is that well that's
that's kind of why I'm wanting our
students in Swire is this something that
the people are often and scared of is it
because there's a lot of technical terms
associated with it that it has a
reputation maybe that you know with
compilers and so on there's a lot of
scary tools and we'll be getting into
those later but do you think it's just
that people often actually doing it
themselves anyway who said if they're
breaking down CSV files or webpage
validation they're doing parsing and
maybe they don't think of what they're
doing the simple thing is parsing right
right a 10 day they might may have gone
across Lexington in their education and
an eider understood that but I thought
it was quite difficult or were too
afraid of it to actually look at it I
don't know exactly but celexa yak is a
newer technology in this area I mean
this it's somewhat hard to use but yeah
really sure about psychology because of
all this because I'm I'm quite happy it
familiar using using technology yeah
yeah I find it's a bit hard to reason
about why people would find it hard I
mean I would tend to agree with the
earth I think the perhaps a lot of
people there's a certain cultural thing
that says it's hard without any
necessarily a basis for it but one of
the reasons for that might be that if we
go back to the example of a web page
validation let's imagine I've got a date
forum you know and someone can type in a
date in u.s. format a British War map
ISO format whatever there's all these
various date formats but so a lot of
that sort of passing it's sort of a
little bit of hand hackery often you
know they'll write things apart and it
can we do all types of passing and using
that technique right I mean of course I
mean you can with this you have a
general-purpose programming language you
can do it with any barging problem that
you want right the only problem is that
it somebody comes very unpleasant doing
it yourself and then you would rather
like to use some well higher level
abstractions a domestic language how
unpleasant would you say I mean are we
talking about impractical all that
there's a lot of corner cases that don't
tend to be done correctly well it just
becomes very tedious right you have to
think of every step in the in the probe
process if you have read this character
then all these cases may occur so
basically a to build up a state machine
with transitions and editing of all the
all the cases
it's very tedious and easy to get wrong
mm-hmm so and another thing that a lot
of people will often use is regular
expressions I mean not most languages
now have a reasonable regular expression
supporting and break this expression to
a relatively powerful is that enough to
do em you all of this passing stuff with
does that solve some of my problems well
so so so definitely some of these so
input for validation problems or even
these Sears or CSV files partners things
you can you can get a long way with with
regular expression and pull programming
and then it's kind of and yes and so
basically regular expressions are well
another way to do parsing it's it's the
next level of from-from parsing manually
I mean writing your own parsing program
completely and regular expressions are
nice because it's it's a yeah it's a
formal language that describes the
declaratively describe say a little
language the structure of a little leg
and but it's not enough so the problem
of regular expression is that I cannot
deal with recursion so as soon as you
have a language that has some kind of
parenthesis right where you have
expressions and have parentheses and
then putting those parenthesis you can
have another expression with parentheses
we have kind of nested expressions then
well we know from formal language theory
that regular expressions don't do the
job so in other words it's the problem
that they can't balance things out if
there's a sort of an open bracket here
but to open brackets they can't sort of
count in the sense that they should be
two at the end yeah okay so that that's
a fairly good reason then why regular
expressions get me further in a sense or
allow me to do more but they still hits
hit a buffer right so in technical terms
a regular expression you can implement
using a state machine the finite state
machine wise we have after reading a
character you have to science which
states to go next and the only thing you
have to remember is which state you are
in which states you are in
and the problem with these with these
parentheses languages that you have to
that you use it yeah you you need a
stack machine because you need to
remember where are you have been okay so
you end up manually coding extra stuff
on top as well as using the regular
expressions again so we're kind of back
to the manual process again effectively
but well as pure regular expression you
cannot do it but then if you can call if
you have some some way of calling
regular expressions and and then you
using defining them by function or
something like that and then you can
emulate the well so you can basically
use the stack after the the function
call stack to emulate the stack and then
you can get this message behavior okay
so then we move on to the sort of the
tools that people know about but before
we get there there's obviously and this
is why academics start getting involved
there's a health theory of passing of
formality and so on so could you give us
an idea of you sort of mentioned about
state machines and so on and could use
an idea of what the the underlying
theory in a sense I mean not going into
too much detail perhaps but of passing
that that solves the problems that
you've talked about the regular
expressions can't balance brackets and
so on but so this goes back to the to
the 50s and so said and to linguistic
Stevens with due to the the study of
natural language so Noam Chomsky in
America was studying natural languages
and he came up with a with a hierarchy
for describing formalizing language
grammars so if people had been thinking
about
about rumors but Chomsky came up with a
formal system to describe describe
languages so so he came up with his idea
of context free grammars the idea there
is that you have a you have a symbol so
called null terminal
and they have productions and
productions can rewrite symbols so
basically there was a system for doing
string view
so my systems were not or parsing so
much as they were for describing the
generation of language the diverging
narrative
glamorous like I said I could recognize
that something was valid no no no they
could generate ascent descent develop
tendencies of air language I said the
idea of context-free grammar so if you
look at the quality grammar you you
write it as a symbol arrow a bunch of
other symbols any idea and then the idea
was that you start with is the start
symbol and then you could look at the
rules of the grammar and and those rules
said well if you have the symbol s then
you can replace it with the symbol down
followed by verb and then now you could
replace by Visionnaire so it's it's it's
describing the valid sentences that I
can build it certainly exactly so it's a
generator for the language rather than
so this is like the implicit rules that
we all learnt from our parents this
thing to them speak when we grow up that
we know that sentences you know Stu have
a noun and a verb and the subject and so
on then we have those rules and Felicity
well so Chomsky program was really can
we understand how language worked and
his theory was that actually our mind
somehow uses such kinds of rules to
describe how we generated sentences of
course so there's a there debate about
whether that actually works for an
opponent for natural language and so for
in addition to to these comics free
grammars you can also have like
sensitive grammars where you say well if
you have this symbol in the context of
terminal symbols then you then you can
rewrite it to this set of simple pass in
other words the actual specific content
of a word changes what I can say
afterwards so let me rephrase that with
the context-free grammars it doesn't
matter I can put any random words and
provided there obey the structure
correctly right but with the
context-sensitive if if I say dog then I
have to say bark I can't say meow or Moo
or something like that yes I'm
simplifying yeah so how does this then
relate to computing power sinks he said
this is right so so down in the early
early sixties people were working on
Algol 60 so this was a
a domain-specific language for defining
algorithms right that was a the problem
at that of the time
and and they wrote so they try to
formalize the design of that language
and sort of had a report about it and so
they come up with this formulation both
the EB and F be enough actually to
beckon our form and
beca's on our kind of independently I
remember came up with this formulation
for describing grammars which was
basically
[Music]
equivalent to come to Chomsky's course
free grammars and so they use these
rules to describe the syntax of
available and
[Music]
gave rise to well a whole lot of work
research about defining languages so
they said the original definition of
Algol 60 this was saying what the valid
syntax was but at that point it was
still a sort of a paper thing in a sense
it when it hadn't been told to
necessarily or not not originally it was
thought of away as just saying here is
the valid syntax of Algol 60 it was a
description language specification
language
so we mentioned earlier about BLF
backus-naur form and we also mention eb
NF so could you just give us a listeners
a brief idea what the difference but
what does the e do is it worth so the e
stands for extended BNF and so VF is
just plain quality grammar so you have a
similar left-hand side and a bunch of
symbols on the right-hand side end you
basically can expand symbols
and so now there are typical patterns in
grammars that you would like to write
down a bit more concisely so the one
typical examples list as you want to
have a list of expressions separated
their commerce typically right in a
canary grammar you would have to define
a non-terminal expression list and then
say one expression is either in a is our
NT or it can be an expression followed
by comma followed by an expression list
and so that's kind of a typical pattern
that you have to write over and over
again and so what EVF does is provides a
high-level construct to allow you to
define a stick so typically in even that
you can write a trash and star and or a
list of expression is 0 to mannington I
can break the expressions it exactly
basically as regular expression
operators 2 to 2 grammars and and if
this is basically just a nice syntactic
convenience because there's this
repeated tedious idiom that you had to
go over and this allows you to do it
nicely right I mean you can you can
define a simple transformation that
transforms a BNF grammars to two basic
BNF
so from an expressive power point of
view there's no difference between the
two just DB and F is a lot more pleasant
to work with right
what comes next if I've got a
description of a language how can I be
familiar with tools like flex and yak
and maybe even Java CC and so on and
they know that they they write some sort
of context free grammar and they'll you
know that they're probably even aware of
the traditional syntax where there's a
little one term on the left-hand side
then there's an arrow and then there's
some stuff on the right-hand side and
that magically they feed this into one
of these tools and then it's some often
it'll generate some code for them that
then read in a text file and does some
magical stuff for them so could you
maybe give us an idea of you know what
are the inputs to these tools you know
the languages are they all context-free
grammars in general and what is the
typical output of at all I mean is it
okay so
yeah so so so the basic idea is that you
write a complex free grammar and feed it
to a tool then there are there are
basically two classes of tools
divided into top divers and bottom up
parser
uhh
and
and in both these classes take a
restrict restricted set subset of the of
the full set of concrete gram
so the idea of a top-down parser is that
it starts with the start symbol and I
said well okay so here are a number of
productions and I can so my sentence
should start with Wall Street shoot
cause it's one of these productions I'm
going to look at the leftmost symbol of
all these productions I can try to see
whether the first word in my string
matches the first word in one of these
productions
so a production is an individual rule
and the grandmas exist here and and then
it goes on and so if it decides about
this production you should take and then
it's as well next we expect this symbol
and we're going to look at the
production of that and eventually you
have a complete tree a problem with
top-down power source is that they
cannot deal with left recursion for
instance two imaginary production where
you have an expression e can be a
expression e followed by the same or
plus followed by our expression in other
words if I if I do the standard
calculator grammar you know so I've got
the exact expression plus expression or
expression minus expression expression
star expression Lia standard simple
mathematics that can't be expressed in
in exactly so so in when you just feed
that into a top-down power source such a
sketchy grammar then it will loop
because it will say well okay I need to
recognize an expression in order to
recognize an expression I'm going to oh
I have to recognize an expression so it
will infinitely loop and and try to it
never makes any progress
you have Baltimore parsers and those are
well Hyuk is the prototypical one of my
bars are the idea there is that you
decide that if you want to
a string or certain symbol then you look
at all productions and try to see if
they can if you can make progress with
any of those productions and there may
be multiple and then at some point you
reach a point where you have reached the
end of a production and then you can
actually say well now can we we can make
a reduction and we can say well we have
recognized this this part of the string
corresponds to this this product and
then you can go up on them okay okay so
we mentioned you know the classic tool I
mean a yak is the one that will keep on
coming back to probably so a lot of
these tools they they take in a grammar
file and and whether it be at the top
down or bottom up passive and a lot of
people will be familiar with them
generating a whole load of code they you
know you feed them in and magically it
generates a C file or a Java file or
something it's that sort of an intrinsic
part of the way a parser needs to work
what why are they doing this well so
essentially what happens is that a
parser generator transforms a grammar
into a into a decision machine a state
machine
the same machine then keeps track of if
if the parsers and it's this data you
see this character on the on the in the
input or this token in the input then go
to this and that that that's how these
things work
and that's where and that's what so what
we were discussing before right so you
can write each tape machine by hand by
him by making if the now statements and
stuff like that but you want to avoid
that and the clever thing of our
generators had a to generate that state
machine for you so when they generate
all this stuff so that's a sort of an
intrinsic part of what they do but one
of the things that if anyone's ever
looked at the file that say yak
generates this there's an awful lot of
stuff in there
I mean resume the it could have just
done that at runtime but by doing it in
advance it's able to pre-compute all
this this is that vision interesting
right right so so so do exactly so toady
the proces of transforming the grammar
into a state machine is often an
expensive process so you want to pre
computer at least well we are if you
have get large grammars this can be
quite an expensive process especially if
you have these LR parser generators with
lots of look ahead and these tables
become huge so you want to definitely
will do that offline but then the other
issue is so so the essential part of
this is that you compute the same
machine and then you could have some
representation of that so it would put
state machine in an external vial and
then read the extra half pound in
advance I mean interpret and that is so
the fact that that person enters
generate code is not really essential
when you could generate the parser well
so yeah you need to representation of
the state machine and then you can
interpret that somehow or you can
generate code that executes the state
machine transitions but there is a
matter of engineering basically okay
okay I think that that will be quite
interesting to a lot of people I said
it's often just a sort of a cultural
expectation they generate codes it's
good that where it is the the sul our
bars are data Tuesday as yes so the
grammar foreign ISM that I have worked
on
it's it actually interprets a file debt
and coach the state machine and it
doesn't show you don't have to generate
a parser for each language you can just
read it in at runtime and but the
computation of the state machine there
is the expensive part thing you will to
just do that once actually basically
okay that's the other thing that anyone
who's used these tools I've I've now
let's imagine I've got a yak thingy I've
generated some code I'm reading it at
runtime so I've got a parser and I give
it some input you know the question is
what does it do next oh we've we've sort
of touched on this that it builds a
trail something so could you talk about
what's often called semantic actions or
parse trees and right so then the
question is so so you you had this
grammar you can recognize so the basic
thing that a parser does or you expect
in I sentences first you could use it in
an in in a web application and recognize
that the input of your form is actually
corrects according to this
index of your view of the language and
then so you could indeed make a parser
for dates right and and but next you
well you probably want to actually use
the structure right I mean we talked to
this in the beginning you actually want
to get the structure of just of the
texture you can do further processing
and so typically so there's an intrinsic
correspondence between a grammar
provides a structure for sentences a
natural tree structure and
so if you look at a common area grammar
it's so let's look at this expression
grammar we have an expression plus an
expression is another expression and the
expression times your question ad an
expression so now if you read the
sentence a plus B times C then the
natural tree representation is all you
have a a plus nodes with a a as a child
and you have an x note which is a child
of this buzz note and as children C and
E B and C probably and so what you could
let a grammar or a parser do is build
this tree structure
so friends DSD f formalism that I
thought that I mentioned before does
exactly so you it's when you bars a
string with its bars or its it will
build a tree structure or term
representation of the texture here first
and then you can use it as an input for
further processing so this is a what a
lot of people call the past rewrite just
right and so can you
so some passes automatically create this
past tree and sometimes some passes you
can either create it manually or you
don't even necessarily have to so for
example the yak type family has this
semantic action and you see this
slightly artificial example perhaps
where they have the calculator grammar
and they actually automatically add
numbers up and multiple so so D the
original philosophy in compilers in the
seventies was well yet you didn't have a
lot of memory and you should really
parse a program and immediately when you
were parsing you should it should
compile it to to machine go and and then
so you have a single linear sweep of
your program that that should do
everything at once because it was easier
because you don't didn't have to read
into the whole program in memory because
well then it just wasn't that much
memory he really had to optimize for
those kinds of thing
so you see that that languages in those
days were designed for this we're
friends Pascal was designed so that what
all definitions became for before uses
right and it was a design to in order to
enable this kinds of processing if you
parse the the your program and then
immediately you could compile it and now
sir parser formalisms were also designed
in such a way that you could actually
rather than building up a tree so they
were there's there's this natural tree
underlying the grammar you would
actually perform semantic actions as a
result of recognizing a production so
then you would attach to a production a
so-called semantic action and which
basically was a statement in your host
programming language yak used see and
you could execute a bit of C code there
and where you can and then well there
was access to the stack so you could
actually access the the children of the
trees and so one way to use these is
actually to in the semantic action build
up a tree that you then could letter
process but you could also do
immediately perform semantic evaluation
so you mentioned the expression
calculator that's there's a standard
example in compiler cores for you boots
instead of built the tree plus a B you
would actually compute
plus the value of a and the value of B
okay so I mean I think what we're
effectively saying there is that back in
the day you mean passing was a very
expensive activity in in computation and
in memory terms so there's there was a
lot of effort to try and make this whole
thing efficient so for example past
trees if you want if you pass a holo
detects bill the big tree it's expensive
so we try and do things as we go along
now that maybe also brings us to a lot
of the thing one of the reasons I think
bypassing scares people is there's a
load of these weird terms ll LR lalr and
so on so can you give us maybe a little
idea of what the history why why are
they there are these various terms maybe
if we can explain some of the major ones
just briefly as a high-level right so
before I mentioned top-down parsing and
bottom-up parsing so these are to do the
fundamental ways to do parsing and so
friendly until down parsing you you say
well very which we should decide on the
production to take by looking at the the
first demo so basically what you were
doing there is a look at the first time
when the inputs and then try to match
that against
the symbols in the in the left hand side
of the production and or you could have
a bit more look at and and share a
decibel ll foraging and LR one is where
you have a look at a 1 and L 2 is where
you have a look at percent of to what
essence so that means the the it's not
not that I look at two things in the
grammar it's two I look ahead to things
in the input cetera okay that's right he
would actually do a bit of a computation
to see if the two watts which tokens
were predicted by symbols and approach
so maybe this is a point actually we
should be explicit of one again maybe
another one of the things that a lot of
these passing out our approaches have
given us implicitly and we don't think
about explicitly we've mentioned tokens
and non terminals so all of these
passing things they're actually based on
the sort of a to face structure ardently
those are the first typically they were
the first stage being I break stuff up
into words you know and simple if I look
at English for example is just of all
the word is separated by space so I just
break everything up so those are the
tokens and and you'll scald those non
terminals no no sort of tokens already
are the words you need so so things like
like plus and an identifier and those
are the terpenes and the non terminals
are the de symbols you know grammars
been things like expression statements
and for loop so those are the things
that don't have a direct they're not
actually in the user input those are
parts of the tree structure so exactly
okay and so those two faces separator so
this is why we have lex and yak for
example lexis doing that first splitting
the things up into words and then yak is
is making the tree structure or the
semantic actions or what okay
sorry so we're going back to the you've
explained ll so then we've got LR and
lalr and those things we're going maybe
we can go over a little bit about those
right so so so LR and Lal are are
variants used in generating
decision tables for bottom-up browsers
shift reduce parser and they are
[Music]
very well technical variations on
deciding which class of glamour grammars
you can actually deal with in a partial
generator so effectively these terms
what were saying if we go back earlier
we talked about context-free grammars
and I think it's fair to say for all
computer languages that most computer
languages were interested in
context-free grammars or what we want
yes you would say so but then people
invent things like offside rules in
Haskell or Python which don't exactly
well we which you cannot express with
the context free grammars unfortunately
I can maybe we'll get onto that later so
that's that's quite interesting but all
these funny symbol terms like ll and LA
and ll are Lal are even are really
saying actually we're taking subsets of
the context-free grammars we're
deliberately cutting down the number of
things we can pass presumably for
efficiency reasons generally good well
the issue is is ambiguities right so if
you do a top-down part you need to
decide which way to go and you can look
a couple of tokens ahead and then you
can decide that if you have to look too
much ahead and you are oh you're
inspecting the string all the time but
but and but for some grammars are prints
these left recursive grammars
there's not enough tokens you can look
at because I can it could be there's not
a fixed number of terms you could look
at to decide where to go what to do
so they restrict Safra top-down parsing
the grammar is restricted to be known
left because it has one example of a
restriction to fit a particular approach
to to do the parsing and so we went back
to the fact that all a lot of this
passing stuff happened in the 1960s and
you know computers were just a tiny
little bit slower then and and so it is
it the case that you know for example if
okay so the ll part type passes have
this obvious limitation but with the LR
parsers they still don't allow me to
express every context-free grammar and
again presumably that is just because
that allowed the very slow computers to
pass text at a reasonable speed well
it's not just slowness it is about
really about algorithmic complexity
because the two early designs a also a
parsing algorithm in 60s called early
parsing and it
actually can deal with all country
grammars well maybe except for circular
once but say basically can can deal with
almost grammars but the complexity of
that algorithm is cubic so it can take
up to and
turrets time to parse the string using
an early okay so if I've understood that
correctly what we're saying there is so
early passing and that's early with with
an e at the end there's an EA RL e ey
rather than just early in the morning
the algorithm I mean it's not
necessarily that it's difficult to
implement throw the purse the poor
person oyster parser it's that the
longer the input potentially it takes
hurt me a cubic amount of time to pass
in other words it can be very very slow
and so when it was invented that I on
computers of the day that would have
taken you know hours possibly to parse a
relatively simple string for the
calculator grammar for example I mean
typically things can get better if you
get lower string and and well so there's
complexity right me it isn't
scalability doesn't doesn't scale to
large this challenge was to have parsing
algorithms that were linear and inhale
and car guarantee linearity refers so is
this still a concern today I mean you
know my phone that the processor I have
of my phone for example is is ten times
the speed of the fastest supercomputer
in the 1960s right but still I mean
complexity beats everything but I mean
if you in it things go and go up fast
so it yeah so it remains a concern you
don't want a exponential parsing
algorithm or even cubic is so is that
why we're still using for example passes
with this LR stuff and and ll and and so
on but we're still the efficiency is
still worth us cutting down the amount
of things we can easily pass just so we
know we can do it very efficiently well
supported earlier just tools around that
that there are basically stuff okay
there they've proven their worth and
they work another advantage of this of
using these subsets is that that if you
succeed in fitting your grammar in this
subset in one of these subsets then
you're guaranteed that your grammar is
not ambiguous but it's kind of so every
it's only ambiguity is a problem where
you can parse a string in more than one
way but so you can say well it might be
an expression but it also might be a
state and that is that is well there's
typically not not what you want when you
define a language but you want to be
clear about what this is the classic
type of ambiguities if I have the
expression two plus three times for now
we implicitly expect that to be 2 plus
brackets 3 times 4 but up a parsec
parsing algorithm thinks well I could
either do that is two plus three
brackets times four or or the other one
and then that's the sort of that's an
example of ambiguity indeed yeah so two
depending on how your formulators the
grammar may be ambiguous to two bars
those kinds of expressions in the okay
so earlier we mentioned about parse
trees now there are two terms that often
come up in passing which is past trees
and abstract syntax trees could you
differentiate between them for us
sure so so parse tree is a tree you get
directly from from parsing according to
the grammar but is so we talked about
this production e is e plus e and so did
the party would get and that is a note
with label E and there's three children
one level e 1 a label plus and one
labeled E and even you may have wide
space in between and you could have in
that in the parse tree as well so it
still maintains you know the tokens
actually the original users text is all
somewhere in there exactly so you can
exactly reproduced did the string from
the content from the tree right so if I
just going over the tree and painting
all the bits of text that are in a
stored in a tree and then you get your
string back there's a one-to-one
correspondence between the the forestry
industry of forests
ok so and then we have abstract syntax
tree right so now of course this this
plus child of this node is not very
interesting because we know well so so
what's what you mean have such an excuse
is transform this parse tree to a tree
where you label
did you notice the trees with the did
the name of the production so for
princess we could use name the the plus
production plus typically and so then we
could transform this e this tree e with
which he'll an e plus and he to a tree
with in the roots label plus and as
children to expression and we throw away
the literal and also a white space and
stuff that because we typically don't
need a for further processing so if I
can try try and repeat that back in it
in another way maybe so if I've got to
say a compiler I do my first pass and I
get back a pass tree which has got all
of the bits of the text in there but
then that's quite low level so then I'll
typically have a phase which would
create me an abstract syntax tree which
will flatten the structure throw away
the bits of the users input they're not
not relevant that are just formatting
related and so on and just leave me with
the essence really of what the user
wanted to say exactly okay and they're
tools of their ways of how does one
create an abstract syntax tree as it
done by hand or well so so some of these
parsing formalisms well we talked about
semantic actions a while ago and there
you see that well the user is actually
in control of building the trees so
typically they're you immediately built
an abstraction extra valid in a parse
tree so there's not this two-stage
process you just build an actual
sentence to be immediately all the
formalism but the advantage of that is
that you actually have to do it but you
have to build a structure and well you
could say well you could actually
derived is representing tree
automatically from the from the from the
grammar because there's a one-to-one
correspondence between grammar parse
trees and abstraction of trees and so
the F is a formation which was designed
to to do that
and so you there's a one-to-one
correspondence between forestry 16x
trees and so yeah and so there's a bit
of so there's an issue why you cannot do
that with all kinds of grammar formulas
because in in in many grammar formalism
you have to do well we talked about
McGee's earlier you have to disambiguate
explicitly and typically you do that for
expressions first by having different
levels of precedence which may encode as
as non-terminal symbols so you have a
level for multiple multiplicative
expressions and additive expressions and
these are different symbols and I want
you get is that you get a so-called
injection so production it's a well
multiplicative expression is well an
additive expression can be a
multiplicative expression or it can be a
additive plus an expression
and then so there's this injection from
going from multiplicative to to additive
this is kind of a well a treat will you
will get a tree note but a single child
and you may have long change of these or
these injections and that death gives
you that that's often why you see that
you want to have this mapping from par
seriously so you'd not only try out
these these literals and a layout which
you also flatten these injection checks
and and then so you have to maybe you
have to and then so that there is so
there's one thing another thing is that
some approaches you use iteration to
express you can have a a long row of B
plus E Plus Z and that's an express as a
as an iteration but in a tree with the
broader I'd like to have a nested tree
structure and then you have to do
transformation to to get from that well
the list of expressions to the nested
structure that is friends of the case
were in in in top-down parsing formulas
we cannot express left recursion and now
so the idea of SDF was that it should be
a formulation where the tree structure
you get is really a one to one
correspondence pretty to the grammar
formalism so you're from the grammar you
can use you know what your tree looks
like
and in order to do that it's it's
couldn't used he's well you shouldn't
you express precedence in the grammar
but you should I you say I just have a
production he is a + e or e times e and
then you have separate dissipation rules
to tell you well this one was left
associative multiplication there's
higher precedence in addition and so
when you do that outside of the
production rules then you don't
contaminate the production rules with
this information and you can actually
get a nice well you see the tree
structure in the grammar so if I've got
that correctly so SDF is a way of fairly
automatically creating or giving
significant help in creating abstract
syntax trees and deferring some of these
decisions about precedents and so on
until the sort of the second stage when
you're creating that abstract syntax
tree rather than when the parse tree is
no no so the idea is not actually a
separation of concerns issue that's how
you can say well you and the grammar do
you just describe several things wanna
see the tree structure if you want to
think about but the logical structure of
them of the of your language elements
and any other is well how should we
parse these things I mean these
expressions should be dynamic you edit
the operator should be parsed in a
particular order and and they said that
you could see that as a separate concern
but as a you're running a compiler
you're interested in the logical
structure of your language not so much
it
disambiguation is kind of a parsing
issue and an SEF allows you to to do
that separation of concerns by having a
separate definition of it is a migration
group which are but they are used within
the bars are so the department takes
care that you don't get immunity but but
you don't have to express it in the in
the grammar
so earlier we were talking about Lex and
yak and we had these two very distinct
phases of breaking the input up into
tokens and then passing it now I believe
that that you were one of the original
people involved in scandalous parsing
where in a sense these two phases are
some how much could you talk to us a
little bit about that please this right
so so I worked on this SDF formalism
which was well designed to have the
natural Help section extry and so what I
did is so we used to have before I
started working on this we had a
traditional two-faced language
definition so that the formalism did
- Alexia ACK you have separates finals
for defining the lexical section of
course finding the Canaries in there in
STFU actually and a single formalism
that allows you to describe the lexical
in dictionaries index so it's already
integrated those issues but the lexical
cynical still described using regular
expressions and character classes
regular expressions starting + and those
kind of thing
and so what I did is turn those so you
just use regular normal context free
grammars to define the lexical CX rather
than just regular expression
and and TRO way to scanner basically so
rather than having a separate stage in
which we tokenized string the parser
reads characters for the tokens or data
are now the characters and we use about
this context-free grammar to both do the
scanning so-called and the departing
bits and so what what advantage does
that game one I mean obviously it's nice
squishing two faces into one but is this
there some does this give me some extra
practical expressive power efficiency or
yeah so for instance oh so we talked
earlier about the limitations of regular
expressions right that you couldn't you
cannot express nested structures
differences think of the problem of
nested comments actually have Java style
long comments and you want to nest these
things that that doesn't work because it
stops at let's see if you comment
opening symbol and and you have another
comment opening symbol and then you have
comment closed corresponding to the
second open example with that it was
just stopped there and stopped parsing
your your comments and when using these
and now using comics free grammars for
Mexico sandesh can actually express
things like nested comments so that is a
little noisy I mean it kind of
generalizes the definition of lexical
syntax from what we had before and and
that was kind of the kind of the
motivation sort of thing that I had in
my teasers and but instead that was not
very strong very strong story I have to
say I mean there were a few small
problems in Pascal that you could could
solve more nicely using this but it was
not really a killer application of
scanner as party
and so I didn't realize until much later
that's well what the real killer
application would be and that is
language combination um so the problem
of combining languages that you
[Music]
I have two combined members and
about why he wants like to come on
language yes levia interesting so we
here at a cogeneration conference and
and one of the so what what you're doing
cogeneration is generate codes Wow
so so what you typically do is write
templates that do cogeneration so you
have some kind of metal language a
template language and you have a bit of
language that you quoted language the
stuff that you generate
that typical tip template engines use
not just generate text or you don't have
any the templates don't have any
structure
and that means that the templates are
not checked syntactically so you cannot
we don't know if they'd be the templates
fragments code fragments are syntax
correct and also you kind of you don't
have the structure of your of your and
the text you generate then you can't do
any further processing unless at least
well you should have to parse after
generation and then it's kind of clumsy
so now using language combination you
can say well okay we define a template
language that is extended with say the
language of girona signature Java so if
we can actually parse the template
fragments using the properties into your
job and then we can see technically
check that these fragments are correct
and then we can also build and use the
underlying abstract in extra to actually
generate every century rather than text
so pursuit before this was difficult
because I Lex and yak effectively those
two faces were very distinct I had to
entirely take my text in and turn it
into words tokenize it and then I would
pass it but if I've got two languages in
a file then they probably don't share
the same tokenization rules presumably
and that would make combining them very
difficult but if I'm using scanner
that's passing it can automatically say
I've reached the java bit now i turn
into the java parser as it were and then
i go back to the template language i
turn into the parser and scanner for
that right so well so there's that
there's a bit of theoretical foundation
for this or the problem is that so much
free grammars are close to the
composition so if you take to construe
grammars and put them together you Evan
you have a new color grammar but if you
take a regular grammar set the one that
is fine used for defining the tokens of
a language regular grammars are not so
close in the composition nor are subsets
of the context-free grammar suggest ll
ll or also L our but can we explain to a
list is what we mean by it's not closed
under composition right so it you take
to Lex files you can put them together
you don't have a new electron it's an
invalid letter far away yes it may not
be a new fella but
probably doesn't follow the restrictions
of the language or it may actually be
one but but because the rules have to be
in some order they may not get the
tokenization that take you one actually
you may have of Florence's keywords of
one language are identifiers in the
other language and then there would be
reserved words so you count long no
longer use those are those those
keywords or the other languages
identifiers in your honor and that is
annoying and references so he says say
you have a a template language it has a
keyword defined and in your java program
you want to use define as an identifier
then if you if you make it combined
grammar then good
generate a Java program with this
keyword define it because it's a keyword
in the template line and that's
a sort of thing that is annoying and now
using this kind of sparring so did the
trick basically is that you do a scanner
is no longer so sure that the problem
really with this combining scanners is
that scanner just goes over string and
she's well this should be an identifier
or she be a keyword without looking at
the context of where you are in the in
the file and now if you do scandalous
parsing the bars are basically steers
the scanning for the tokenization it
says well at this point I expect a Java
identifier in well it will look for Java
and inspire and at some other point it
will look at a so here I'm expecting a a
template engine key war to is I have to
find here so is this a context-sensitive
grammar then we make Genesis a bit it's
a bit confusing isn't it accomplished
free grammar that this context that it
is still context-free it is College free
but it still provides context that's
there's always a bit counterintuitive so
let's see if we can now you're right I
mean so this is just it still is a
contra grammar but it is so you do
scanning in the context of of a
particular symbol so it maintains all
the sort of the theoretical niceness of
context-free grammars exactly yes okay
so given that we're sort of moving into
this future possibly where we're getting
lots of domain-specific languages we're
embedding them in scandalous parsing is
probably a significant way of enabling
this something that was very difficult
to do before so do you see this is the
sort of the killer application for
scandalous parsing absolutely yes yes I
mean we have been doing really great
things due to the fact that we had this
careless parsing algorithm
so we've been embedding dementia free
languages into Java we've been building
code generation tools where we embed the
source and target language into the meta
language so it became ours fragments of
of those languages
yeah and I think you only get advice
using something like an inspiring and
and the techniques are there lying yes
yes okay except well I would agree it
sounds like a very a really great way of
moving things forward I think probably
be seeing an awful lot more scandalous
passing as we move into this so the
world so I think that's probably
something for every will to keep an eye
on Elka visher thank you very much
thanks thanks for downloading and
listening to software engineering radio
software engineering radio is an
educational program brought to you by
hillside Europe if you want more
information about the podcast and all
the other episodes visit our website and
s/ii - radio dot length if you want to
support us you can donate to the SE
radio team via the website or you can
advertise press your radio for example
by clicking on the Digg reddit delicious
and slash dot buttons to contact the
team please send email to team at s e -
radio net or if it is specific to an
episode please use the comments facility
on the website so other people can react
to your comments this episode of se
radio as well as all other episodes are
licensed under a creative commons 2.5
license please see the website for
details thanks to Charlie Crowell and
the pod safe music network for the music
used in the show the song is called
Vegas hard rock shuffle
[Music]